I was invited along to a party in Notting Hill, which in those days was not the
smart Notting Hill you now know.
Invited to a party by a friend of mine who was trying to make a living as an
independent filmmaker, a man called Morris Hatton.
And suddenly my wife and I turned up. This would be in early 1965.
I'd just become deputy editor of the magazine News Society.
And my friend Morris said, here's a chap you should meet.
And so Cedric appeared looming through the grey smoke of a party of that kind.
And we went out into the garden so we could hear each other speak.
And Cedric said, well, yes, News Society, he said, News Society.
excellent magazine, not enough jokes, you should meet my friend Bannam.
That was the architecture and design critic Peter Rayner Bannam,
whom I'd never met.
And I thought, well, that's an idea.
So next day I rang Bannam,
who became our architecture and design correspondent,
and he wrote some wonderful articles,
often of a kind that might have been inspired by Cedric in a way.
he would take some perfectly ordinary object, I mean one of the best known cases was
the
manufacture of an ice cream cornet, or the growth of the new kind of crisp, not the
old
fashioned crisp but a very special crisp with special flavors, and analyze it with
all the
techniques of an art historian, as if he were looking at a Giotto or Guido Renna or
whatever.
And so I was very grateful to Cedric for that, and we continued to see each other.
And
the thing about that joke was that I think that Cedric realised that jokes and wit
were one way
to put your point across. So many people think that to put your point across you've
got to be
deeply serious and boring all the time, which Sadiq wasn't. From that meeting we
saw each other a lot. New South also thought that there were things to be
said for jokes and for provoking people and there was a lot of discussion at
that time as indeed there is now. What exactly the role of Parliament was, was
it properly representing the majority of the country, was it buried in a little
whole of its own that wasn't very interesting. And one of the phrases of the day was
pop-up.
It is again now isn't it, we talk about pop-up restaurants. Anyway it was in there
then.
I thought well let's have a pop-up parliament. Let's pull down this old Gothic
thing, over
and done with, not entirely seriously of course, and replace it with something high
tech and
all that. So I rang Cedric up and said, would he like to write that? Now I didn't
realise
what I was getting myself into because Cedric was not a writer actually, not in the
novel
sense of the word. He was a spark off of ideas, brilliant actually. But like many
architects,
it's not unusual to find architects can't write. It doesn't somehow fit with their
discipline.
You get a series of statements, but not a persuasive article. And this article we
talked
about for quite a long time, and it didn't come, and it didn't come, and it didn't
come.
And Cedric was then in his, not in the office that he became famous for in Alfred
Place,
but it was in George Street behind the Wallace Collection. So I wandered along
there, and
I said, Cedric, we're going to have to talk this article through. And eventually the
article
did appear as by Cedric Price, but if you persevere to the end there's little
footnotes
saying this article is the result of many conversations between the editor and Mr
Price.
Well as you might imagine, it was, like everybody in the 60s, it was important to
clear the
space so you pulled the existing building down, you didn't try to adapt it in any
way
And you created something which very much depended on electronic and technological
instant
communication between voters and members of parliament.
So you didn't have the members of parliament here in this lovely box and the voters
out
here whom you consulted once every five years.
The idea was to create a continuous dialogue.
dialogue. Would have been hell actually probably. That was the idea. And actually in
a funny
sort of way with the arrival of social media, something like that is actually
happening.
I'm sure members of parliament feel for better or worse really. They're drawn much
more.
So it was a beginning shot at that time. And I don't think either Cedric or I
thought this
with a project that anyone would ever build or demolish. But it was a way of pushing
the
argument forward through built form rather than just simply stating what you felt.
And so it was sometime after that that Cedric approached me with the idea for
Pottery's
Thinkbelt because given the experience of the Pop-Up Parliament where he
realized that I could get blood out of a stone editorially, in other words
something that a general public might read as opposed to an architectural
public. Potteries Thinkbelt was to be cited in the landscape where Cedric was
was a child, in fact. North of Birmingham you have this area called the Potteries,
for
the obvious reason that that is where the one element in the Industrial Revolution
began.
It was an area of manufacture of ceramics at one end, or simply old-fashioned plates
and dishes at the other. At the top of the ladder was a Wedgwood family, who created
who created a very special kind of English ceramics.
And at the bottom were people who were making just mugs to put your tea in.
And it was a big business.
But like a lot of businesses in the post-war period in Britain,
it had gone into decline.
In fact, it had been going into decline for quite a long time,
partly through international competition
and partly through just bad practice by the people running the factories who were
very
reluctant to invest new money in it.
So it was a rather desperate area, and in some ways if you were to go there now it's
still a rather desperate area.
There was nothing beautiful about it.
No money had been put into buildings.
And Cedric's idea was to take this area, which he knew well, take the example of an
attempt
to build a new university there at a place called Keele, which had never been very
successful.
It was always a rather timid launch.
It was always looking over its shoulder at other people.
And he wanted to create something which would build on the existing rail network to
an extent,
because the place was festooned with small railway lines because of the industrial
background.
It was quite easy to get from one place to the other.
And he envisaged starting a university of 20,000 students immediately, who would go
from place to place, rather than building an aesthetically wonderful university.
would have this thing which was more closely integrated with the community, you
would have
the community making much more use of the university. You wanted to have more people
drawn in. Other people at the time were thinking already of using mass media,
particularly
the newly popular television, which it's hard to think had a time when it was not
popular,
but anyway it was only becoming popular. And not very far away they created
something called
the Open University, which was based on the mass media and based in the new town of
Milton
Keynes. And in a strange way, the Open University was building on Cedric's idea, but
not using
anything of the built form at all. They were just using the content.
I'm just writing a long article about Nonplan because of the four people who wrote
it, I'm
I'm the only one still alive. I'm an exhibit from the past.
And the two moving spirits on this attempt to again jolt people into thinking about
what is the purpose of planning.
planning the two moving space with myself and a geographer called Peter Hall, who
has
just himself died and I'm just in the middle of writing a sort of tribute piece for,
which
is basically about how he and I collaborated on non-plan.
Though he became a planner and great figure of a quite different sort, but at that
time,
like the rest of us in the mid-60s.
We thought you could play around with anything really.
Anything went really, was the point, intellectually as well.
And Peter wrote for us a very great deal
on matters of urban change, often on planning.
But also he had a wide grasp of so many subjects, particularly based on his
experience of America.
And both of us were dismayed and made angry by how modernist planning and
architecture
had worked out on the ground, not what it was like in a book by Le Corbusier, but
what
it was like when you built it.
And particularly of course the claims that both planners and architects at the time
usually
made for the way they were able to reshape the society that they were in, which
involved
a great deal of demolition of existing property, which could have been reused.
I lived in the East End of London which was being destroyed by planning schemes,
almost
more than it had been destroyed by the Luftwaffe.
So Peter and I were having a bite to eat and we thought to ourselves, well, would it
be
any worse if there was no planning at all?
After all, the cities we've got weren't planned.
They just grew up over centuries and planners had this program.
Architects, particularly modernist architects, had this program.
For example, the tower blocks were an excellent idea for families.
It was one of the more obvious things.
And it was just an unhappy situation.
And once again, rather than purely say that,
we thought we should try to demonstrate it.
And as we were talking, the idea of something called non-plan,
which now I've entered the language a bit, cropped up.
In other words, we should have a special issue of the magazine
which would propose the idea that if we had no planning,
if we perhaps listened to what people wanted for their houses
as opposed to imposing something on them, perhaps it would be okay.
And so we agreed to do that. We also thought we should have some fellow writers on
this.
And the two writers we went to immediately, there was no question about it, was
Cedric,
who was the most iconoclastic architect we knew, and Banham, the man he'd originally
recommended to us and both of them immediately said yes. The structure of non-plan
was that
there would be a couple of general articles, an introduction and a conclusion. And
in between
those, in order to infuriate people, because that was part of the point, there would
be
three case studies of bits of England that might be improved, we would argue,
destroyed
other people might argue, by being treated as areas that could be subjected to
non-plan.
It took quite a long time to write because I became editor of the magazine in early
1968.
1968 was a year of explosions throughout the world on the student campuses and there
were
lots of other things to write about apart from writing about non-plan.
But we did eventually write it. I wrote both the introduction, Peter and I wrote
most of
the conclusion. Bannum decided to write about East Anglia as the set piece example.
Peter
Hall wrote about East Midlands. Cedric himself wrote about the area of the New
Forest on
South Coast, which again, as in the case of the Thinkbelt, he knew well that
apparently
he'd moved there to escape bombing during the war and had spent quite a bit of time
with his grandfather, I think. Everybody wrote bits and put it together and we
published
it in the Special History. And it's quite interesting, it provoked a mixture of
anger
and sort of stunned silence. People couldn't believe that we were making this
suggestion
because planning was one of those sacred things.
If something wasn't planned, it wasn't quite real, really.
I mean, there's an excellent book by a historian called Tony Yud,
which is just called Post-War,
and he takes the whole of Western Europe
and tries to understand whether,
in partial imitation of the Soviet system or for some other reason, everything was
much
better if it was planned rather than if it was just allowed to happen, which was a
new
idea really, and of course in many places has now dwindled. But I would say that in
England at any rate in the 1960s the idea that everything had to be planned. You
needed
to get the facts and the figures, then you plan something. It was at its height. And
a lot of people made a living out of this kind of thing, either as professionals or
as teachers or whatever. And people ask themselves, well, is this anarchy, letting
anything happen,
Or is it kind of a covert new form of capitalism where you're just providing a new
market so
people can make their money out of it?
A bit of both, really.
The philosopher Wittgenstein had a theory.
He didn't mind what he ate, provided it was always the same.
And in terms of appearance, that was Cedric.
He was always dressed the same, with his striped black-white shirt, his loose
collar, his black
knitted tie is cigar and if you were talking to him at the office it was a glass of
brandy.
That was Cedric. An amazingly recognisable figure. The office he was mostly known
for
was an office in a side street called Alfred Place, not far from the main buildings
of the
University of London, not very far either from the post office tower which Peter
Rainer Branham
once said it was the only building that had been built since the Second World War in
London
that could deserve a space in the same skyline as St Paul's Cathedral. So, you know,
very
much Cedric territory. The office was above a shop of some sort. I can't remember
what
the shop was. So you went up some stairs, got the top, and there was... when you got
the top of the stairs there was some unfortunate character who was some kind of
assistant sitting
there whose main job as far as I could see was to make sure that the radio was
always turned to
Radio 4 and he would probably have talked to one or two of these assistants, Steve
Mullin, Will
Alsop. There was always some such person there but Cedric wouldn't be there. Cedric
would be one stage
further up in the building in the white room, which was a room painted white. It was
a quite
large room. It was the full width of the building, I think. And there would be piles
of papers
and bits of drawings and all the rest of it. You'd be offered a glass of brandy,
because
there was always a glass of brandy, and you would talk for the next two hours, which
is
which is why you couldn't gather that often because you had other things to do.
But it was always very enjoyable and from time to time somebody else would bob up,
the General Secretary of the trade union movement or whoever.
He was a very generous host when he gave a party.
And he came round here to our house a few times.
times. The first time he came he deeply embarrassed my wife because he'd gone
upstairs to wash his
hands and he came back down and said he'd never seen such a beautiful object. I
thought what on
earth has he seen? Sally had been trying to save soap by moulding the old bits of
soap together,
you see, sort of some blue, some brown, some yellow, some white in a beautiful ball.
So he
They brought this all down to tell us that was the future.
Curiously, there's a Palestinian activist and philosopher
called Edward Said.
He's one of the founders of the Divine Orchestra
between Israelis and Palestinians,
and very much the New York intellectual.
But he told a friend of mine that the height of his career
was when he went to a dinner party in Manhattan somewhere, and his fellow guest was
Sid Charisse,
the dancer for An American in Paris. Well, when Cedric was in Las Vegas for some
event,
I don't think he was a gambler, but he would believe very strongly in the ethos of
Las
Vegas, as you get in the Venturi book on learning from Las Vegas. That was his
scene. And he
was in a restaurant sitting there having his supper with a friend. And he noticed
across
the dance floor in the restaurant there was Cid Charisse sitting there. Well, Cid
Charisse
never wanted to lose his opportunities of this kind, so he went across to Cid
and said, can I have a dance?
And so the height of that trip, and perhaps of more than that
for Cedric, was that that was the night
I danced with Cedris.
It's something that I never managed
to pin down in talking to him, the extent to which he would
have liked, really in his heart, to have built more.
He always maintained, at least in talking to me,
that yes, he did want to build more,
but there was this problem with the bureaucrats
and there was that problem.
But I'm not sure. I think for him building was a kind of dialogue.
And of course he did such beautiful drawings in particular.
Whatever I may half jokingly say about him as a writer, he was brilliant.
As a speaker, his lectures were wonderful. I went to a few of them.
And he could just take an audience and turn them around in his hand.
And teach people not through long, elaborate arguments, but through jokes, through
observations,
through asking questions to which there was no obvious answer.
And I think it's an intellectual power that he has.
I can't see, speaking as a non-architect, I can't see much evidence that
architecture
has gone in a way that he would approve of.
I can't see that at all.